Guide to the Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers 1587-1960 PR 47
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation, 1587-1960, undated; 17.63 Linear feet in 33 flat file folders and 6 boxes
  - Subseries I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection, 1587-1921, undated; 16 Linear feet in flat files and three boxes
    - Print No. 454. Mezzotint: "This Portrait of Captn. Isaac Hull, of the United States Navy...", 1813 (Folder FF-14)
      Full title: "This portrait of Captn. Isaac Hull, of the United States Navy, also the representation of the most interesting scene during the Action, between the United States Frigate Constitution, and his Britannic Majesty's Frigate Gurriere, is most respectfully dedicated to the People of the United States, by their fellow Citizen, T.W. Freeman." Gilbert Stuart Esqr. Pinxit. Freeman, Excudit. The Vignette, from an Original Drawing, under the direction of Captn. Hull. Published at Philadelphia, & Entered according to Act of Congress, the 1st day of February 1813, by Freeman & Pierie, of the State of Pennsylvania. Large portrait of Isaac Hull at top. Vignette below of the engagement between the "Constitution" and the "Guerriere". First state, dedicated by T.W. Freeman.
    - Print No. 457. Mezzotint: "Iohn Paul Iones, Commander of a Squadron in the Service of The Thirteen United States of North America, 1779.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Artist, engraver and publisher not named. A British print attributed to Richard Brookshaw.
    - Print No. 459. Mezzotint: "Iohann Paul Iones, Befehlshaber einer Schwadron in Diensten Der 13. Vereinigten Provinzen Von Nord – Amerika, 1779.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      I.E. Haid Sculp. zu finden in Augsburg bey I. I. Haid u. Sohn.
    - Print No. 460. Mezzotint: "Capt. John Paul Jones, Commander of a Squadron of Ships in the Service of France and America.", 1780 (Folder FF-4)
      Done from an Original, designed at Amsterdam. London, Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett, Map & Printsellers, No. 53, Fleet Street; as the Act directs, 7th. Feby. 1780.
    - Print No. 461. Engraving: "John Paul Jones"., 1781 (Folder FF-4)
      Tels hommes rarement se peuvent presenter, Et quand le Ciel des donne, il faut en profiter. Moliere. Gloire du Val de grace. Dessine d'apres nature au mois de May 1780 par J.M. Moreau le Jeune Grave a l'Eauforte par J.M. Moreau le Je. Termine au burin par J.B. Fosseyeux 1781. Beauble scripsit. A Paris chez l'Auteur rue du Coq St. Honore, pres. Le Louvre. A.P.D.R.
    - Print No. 462. Engraving: "John Paul Jones. Commodore au Service des Etats-Unis de l'Amerique, tel qu'il etait dans le combat du 23. 7bre 1779, contre le Comodore Pearson. son Vaisseau le bon home Richard montait 40. canons. ….", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Dessine par C:J: Notte. Grave par Carl Guttenberg, a Paris chez Guttenberg rue St. Hyacinthe la 2me porte par la place St Michel. Undated. Autographed by C. Guttenberg.
    - Print No. 463. Mezzotint: "Iohn Paul Iones, Commodore au Service des Etats-Unis de l'Amerique, tel qu'il etait dans le combat du 22 Fbre 1779. contre le Capt. Pearson, son Vaisseau le bon home Richard montait 40. canons. …", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Dessine par C.F. Notte. se vende chez F.M. Will. a Augsbourg.
    - Print No. 464. Engraving: "The Celebrated Paul Jones.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Artist, engraver and publisher not named. A rare contemporary portrait of Jones, imaginary in character, undoubtedly published in England.
    - Print No. 467. Engraving: "Paul Jones the Pirate.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Artist and engraver not named. Pub. by A. Park, 47, Leonard St. Tabernacle Walk, London.
    - Print No. 468. Engraving: "Mr. Goff as Paul Jones.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      "No. 98" in lower left-hand margin. Artist and engraver not named. Publication line reading: "London, Published April. 9, 1832, by Orlando Hodgson, 10, Cloth Fair." is missing on this copy.
    - Print No. 475. Engraving: "Com. Thomas Macdonough Of The United States Navy.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Engraved by T. Gimbrede N. York. Second state, omitting the attribution of the drawing to Thomas Gimbrede. (See No. 779.)
    - Print No. 477. Engraving: "Commodore McDonough." "82.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Designed and aquatinted by (no engraver named). Published by P. Price, Philadelphia. Second state according to Stauffer, the first state containing the name of the engraver.
    - Print No. 479. Engraving: "Comre. Oliver H. Perry of the U.S. Navy.", undated (Folder FF-5)
      Engraved by Thos. Gimbrede. Companion to the portrait of "Comre. Thomas Macdonough", engraved by Thomas Gimbrede and published by Michl. H. Bowyer (No. 476, not in N-YHS collection).
    - Print No. 480. Engraving: "Comre. Oliver H. Perry.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Engraved by Henry Meyer from an original Picture by John W. Jarvis. Companion to the portrait of "Comre. Stephen Decatur", engraved by Henry Meyer (No. 445, not in N-YHS collection).
    - Print No. 487. Engraving: [Thomas Truxtun], undated (Folder FF-4)
      No title. Drawn and engraved by St. Memin, Philadelphia. In black and white.
    - Print No. 489. Lithograph: "Naval Heroes of the United States. No. 1. Battle of Lake Erie.", 1846 (Folder FF-4)
      Oval portraits of Oliver H. Perry, James Lawrence, Stephen Decatur, David Porter, Johnston Blakeley and William Bainbridge around view in center of Perry's Victory on Lake Erie. Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York. Copyrighted by N. Currier, New York, 1846.
    - Print No. 490. Lithograph: "Naval Heroes of the United States. No. 2. Battle of Lake Champlain.", 1846 (Folder FF-4)
      Oval portraits of Thomas Macdonough, Charles Stewart, Isaac Hull, Wm. Henry Allen, Jacob Jones and Joshua Barney around view in center of Macdonough's Victory on Lake Champlain. Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York. Copyrighted by N. Currier, New York, 1846.
    - Print No. 491. Lithograph: "Naval Heroes of the United States. No. 3. Bon Homme Richard and Serapis.", 1846 (Folder FF-4)
      Oval portraits of John Paul Jones, Alexander Murray, Richard Dale, Nicholas Biddle, John Barry and Edward Preble around view in center of the engagement between the "Bon Homme Richard" and the "Serapis". Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York. Copyrighted by N. Currier, 1846, New York.
    - Print No. 492. Lithograph: "Naval Heroes of the United States.", 1846 (Folder FF-4)
      Oval portraits of Perry, Decatur, Macdonough, Preble, Barney, Barry, Dale, and Bainbridge around view in center of a sailor nailing a flag to a mast. Kelloggs & Thayer, New York. Copyrighted by Kelloggs & Thayer, 1846, New York.
    - Print No. 493. Engraving: Sheet of twelve small engraved medallion portraits, undated (Folder FF-5)
      Twelve small engraved medallion portraits of "James Lawrence Esqr. Late of the United States Navy"; "Jacob Jones Esqr. of the United States Navy"; "Robert Fulton Esqr."; "Major Genl. Andrew Jackson"; "Isaac Hull Esqr. of the United States Navy"; "General Pike. Late of the United States Army"; "James Munroe President of the United States"; "William Bainbridge Esqr. of the United States Navy"; "Oliver H. Perry Esq. Minister Plenipotentiary of the U.S."; "Major Genl. Brown, U.S. Army"; and "Major Genl. Winfield Scott. of the United States Army", with two small circular engraved views of naval engagements below, inscribed: "The U.S. Frigate Constitution Isaac Hull Esqr. Commander Capturing His B.M.'s Frigate Guerriere August 19th. 1812", and "The U.S. Frigate United States Stephen Decatur Esqr. Commander Capturing His B.M's Frigate Macedonian October 25th. 1812." Artist, engraver and publisher not named. Undated. This sheet was published by Ch. Bance, Paris.
    - Print No. 494: Silhouettes. "Heroes of the War with England in 1812.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Three silhouette portraits of: Capt. Wm. Vaughan, Sacketts Harbor, 1813; Brig. Gen. Zebulon M. Pike, 1813; Capt. Isaac Chauncey, Kingston Harbor, 1812. Title and identification in manuscript. "Three American officers prominent in the military and naval operations on Lake Ontario during the War of 1812." "Of contemporary origin."
    - Print No. 495. Aquatint: "John Pierce who was murdered...", undated (Folder FF-5)
      "John Pierce who was murdered by a Shot from the Leander a British 50 Gun Ship fourth rate Commanded by Henry Whitby, the Cambrian of 44 Guns, & Driver of 20 Guns, within a quarter of a mile of Sandy Hook on Friday at 5. o.Clock P.M. 28th of April 1806. Design'd & Engraved by the Publisher Published According to Act of Congress by John James Barralet.
    - Print No. 496. Engraving: "Splendid Victories gained by the United States Frigates over the British since the commencement of the present War"., 1813 (Folder FF-4)
      Center of the print consists of three vertical oval panels containing views of actions between the "United States" and "Macedonian"; "Constitution" and "Guerriere"; and "Wasp" and "Frolic". The names of "Decatur", "Hull" and "Jones" are set forth on ribbons above the panels, the name of "Bainbridge" appearing below that of "Hull". At bottom of print is a statement giving dates, places of action, commanders and results. New Haven March 20th. 1813. Published by A. Doolittle Engraver.
    - Print No. 497. Engraving: "Le Fameux Commodor Paul Jones, Americain.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Artist and engraver not named. A Paris, chez Bonnet, rue St. Jacques, au coin de celle de la Parcheminerie.
    - Print No. 499. Etching: "Capt. Iohn Paul Iones,", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Artist and engraver not named. An early Dutch print of Jones.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (a) Views of New York City (Folder -)
    - Print No. 501. Lithograph. "La Nouvelle Yorck.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Full title: "La Nouvelle Yorck. Ville scitue dans l'Amerique septentrionale dans l'Isle de Manahatan pres l'embouchure du fleuve hudson, Les Hollandois commencerent a la batire en l'annee 1615 et la nommerent nouvelle Amsterdam, mais en 1666, il en furent prives par les Anglois, qui la nommerent la nouvelle Yorck." Printed in Paris by J. Chereau. At the top, printed from right to left - "Vue de la nouvelle Yorck"
    - Print No. 504. Lithograph: "New York And The Narrows Taken Going Up The Hudson.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      L.E.F. Du Roos. fect. Printed by C. Hullmandel.
    - Print No. 505. Lithograph: "New York Bay. From the Telegraph Station.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Lith. & Pub. by N. Currier, 2 Spruce St. N.Y. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 506. Lithograph: "View On The Harlem River, N.Y. The Highbridge In The Distance.", 1852 (Folder FF-5)
      View of Macomb's Dam. Drawn by F.F. Palmer. Lithographed by Currier & Ives. Copyrighted, 1852. Second state. Colored by hand. Duplicate of No. 47 (not in N-YHS collection).
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (b) Revolutionary War (Folder -)
    - Print No. 518. Engraved French representation of "Indépendance Des États-Unis.", 1786 (Folder FF-4)
      Circular print in colors at top, containing stone monument inscribed: "L'Amérique Et Les Mers, Ô Louis! Vous Reconnaissent Pour Leur Libérateur", with small oval portraits on upper shaft of monument entitled: "Louis Seize", "Franklin" and "Waginston". Cock on blue globe decorated with fleur-de-lis at top of shaft. Palm trees and Indian maiden at right, with her left foot on the head of the British lion. Sea and sailing ships in background at left. Below the print is a two-column description in French of the Declaration of Independence. Duplessis Berteaux del. L. Roger Sculp. 1786. A Paris chez Blin, Imprimeur en Taille-Douce, Place Maubert, No. 17, vis-à-vis la rue des 3 Portes. A.P.D.R.
    - Print No. 522. Engraved map: "A Plan of New York Island with part of Long Island, Staten Island & East New Jersey, 1776 (Folder FF-5)
      "A Plan of New York Island with part of Long Island, Staten Island & East New Jersey … Engagement on the Woody Heights of Long Island between Flatbush and Brooklyn on the 27th of August 1776 between His Majesty's Forces, commanded by General Howe and the Americans under Major General Putnam…." Engraved & Publish'd … Octr 19th 1776 by Wm. Faden … Charing Cross, London.
    - Print No. 526. Engraving: "Saratoga. Le 17 Octobere 1777. le général Burgoine avec 6040 Soldats bien disciplinés met bas les armes devant les milices Americaines nouvellement tirees de l'Agriculture et conduite par Horatio Gates.", undated (Folder FF-4)
      Description of campaign in French below the title. Dessiné par Fauvel Gravé par Godefroy de l'Academie Impériale et Royale de Vienne etc. Colored by hand.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (c) Miscellaneous Historical Prints (Folder -)
    - Print No. 547. Painting: "Africa and America"., 1807 August 31 (Box 1)
      Signed by T. Hinton, 44 well St. Two-section painting in colors on glass, inscribed "Africa" and "America". Africa represented by black woman; scarf in her left hand, curved bow in her right hand. Recumbent lion at her right. America represented by white woman holding American flag. Two frigates at left. Monument and urn at right with small portraits of Washington and Franklin.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (e) Early Maps of America (Folder -)
    - Print No. 572. Engraved map in colors of North America: "North America Divided into its principall Parts where are distinguished the severall States which belong to the English, Spanish and French.", 1680 (Folder FF-33)
      Title continues, "To the Most Serene and Most Sacred Majesty of Charles II. By the Grace of God King of Great Brittain, France, and Ireland. This Map of North America is humbly Dedicated and Presented By Your Majesties Loyal Subject and Servant William Berry." Sold by William Berry at the Sign of The Globe between Charing Cross and White-Hall. 1680.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (f) Portraits of George Washington and Views of Mount Vernon (Folder -)
    - Print No. 579. Mezzotint: "George Washington, Esqr. General and Commander in Chief of the Continental Army in America.", 1775 (Folder FF-4)
      Done from an Original Drawn from the Life by Alexr. Campbell of Williamsburgh in Virginia. Published as the Act directs. 9 Septr. 1775 by C. Shepherd. Portrait of Washington with drawn sword astride a prancing horse. Battle in distance at right. Colored by hand. Hart 721. Baker 46. This print, published in London about two months after Washington took command of the Continental Army at Cambridge, Mass., on July 3, 1775, is one of two portraits of Washington published the same day by C. Shepherd, London, which are the earliest dated engraved portraits of Washington. A copy of this print was sent to Mrs. Washington by Gen. Joseph Reed, President of the Continental Congress. George Washington, under date of January 31, 1776, replied: "Mrs. Washington desires I will thank you for the picture sent her. Mr. Campbell, whom I never saw to my knowledge, has made a very formidable figure of the Commander-in-Chief, giving him a sufficient portion of terror in his countenance."
    - Print No. 584. Engraving: "George Washington Late President of the United States of America,...", 1800 (Folder FF-17)
      Full title: "George Washington Late President of the United States of America, This Plate is Humbly Dedicated to the Friends of the above Gentleman, by their most Obedient Humble Servt. P. Roberts" Engraved by P. Roberts. Painted by W. Birch, Esq. Of Carolina. Full bust portrait, set in a medallion, surrounded by flags and implements of war. Head three-quarters to right. Colored by hand. Hart 274. Baker 389. This print was published at London on April 10, 1800 by P. Roberts.
    - Print No. 599. Small engraved profile bust portrait of Washington in uniform, without title., undated (Folder FF-4)
      Drawn from the life by Du Simetiere in Philadelphia. Engraved by B.L. Prevost at Paris. No. I. First state. In black and white. Undated. Same portrait as No. 408 (b)(not in N-YHS collection). Companion to portrait of John Dickinson; see No. 672. (No. 599 was removed from the collection for the George Washington exhibition in 1998-99 and was not returned as of February 2019.)
    - Print No. 620. Lithograph, colored: "Mount Vernon.", undated (Folder FF-5)
      Drawn on the spot and in colors by C.H. Wells. Printed in oil colors by F. Collins. View of Mount Vernon from the side, with the Potomac River in the distance. Small oval panel of Washington's tomb in center of bottom margin.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (g) Naval Prints of Revolutionary War, War of 1812, and War with Algiers (Folder -)
    - Print No. 624. Lithograph: "Paul Jones.", undated (Folder FF-5)
      "Paul Jones. Attaque une Flotte Anglaise commandée par Pearson, revenant de la Baltique en 1793." First state. Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Published by V. Turgis, Paris. "18" in center above the title. (See No. 82 supra for second state.)
    - Print No. 626. Engraving: "The U.S. frigate Constitution Commanded by Isaac Hull, Esqr....", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Full title: "The U.S. frigate Constitution Commanded by Isaac Hull, Esqr. Captured his B.M. frigate Guerriere Capt. Dacres In 30 Minutes On the 19th. of August 1812." Pubd. by Chs. D. Veechio, 136 Broad Way. Second state of an engraving originally designed, engraved and published by Thomas Gimbrede. Colored by hand. Duplicate of No. 128 supra.
    - Print No. 627. Engraving: "The U.S. frigate Constitution Commanded by Isaac Hull, Esqr....", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Duplicate of Print No. 626; see full description above.
    - Print No. 633. Water color photograph of the painting "The "Wasp and the Frolic", undated (Folder FF-17)
      The water color photograph is of a painting by Thomas Birch depicting the action on October 18, 1812 between the "Wasp" and the "Frolic", now owned by The New-York Historical Society.
    - Print No. 634. Engraving: "This Representation Of The U.S. Frigate United States...", undated (Folder FF-5)
      "This Representation Of The U.S. Frigate United States, Stephen Decatur Esqr. Commander, Capturing His Britannic Majesty's Frigate Macedonian, John S. Carden Esqr. Commander, Is respectfully inscribed to Capt. Stephen Decatur … by … James Webster." Vignette of Decatur at base. Painted by T. Birch, A.C.S.A. Engraved by S. Seymour. Subscription Price $5.00. Colored by hand. Later impression of No. 162 (not in N-YHS collection).
    - Print No. 639. Engraving: "The Capture of H.B.M. Frigate Java...", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Full title: "The Capture of H.B.M. Frigate Java, Capt. Lambert, by the U.S. Frigate Constitution, Com. Bainbridge, on the 29th Decr. 1812, Lat. 13° 6' S. Long. 38° W. off the Coast of Brazil, after an engagement of 1 hour & 55 minutes." Designed & Engraved by N. Jocelin. In black and white.
    - Print No. 651. Lithograph: "Perry's Victory On Lake Erie. Fought Sept. 10th 1813 ….", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Lithographed and published by J. Baillie, New York, and J. Sowle, New Bedford, Mass. Later state of No. 273 supra. Reference to J. Sowle almost obliterated.
    - Print No. 651A. Woodcut: "A View of Col. Johnson's Engagement with the Savages (commanded by Tecumseh) near the Moravian Town, October 5, 1812.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      A. Bowne Sc. Rectangle. Partially colored by hand.
    - Print No. 653A. A pair of engravings, framed separately. (A) "Key To B. Tanner's Print of Macdonough's Victory On Lake Champlain, and Defeat of the British Army at Plattsburg by Genl. Macomb. September 11th 1814.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      This key contains engraved sketch of the scene depicted in print by Benjamin Tanner (Print No. 652; not in N-YHS collection), with numerals on the face of sketch which are keyed to the names of ships and their commanders in text below this sketch. Extracts from Come. Macdonough's official Letter are also published. Companion to the below plan (No. 653B). Duplicates of Nos. 299 (a) and 299 (b) supra.
    - Print No. 653B. A pair of engravings, framed separately. (B) "Plan of the Siege of Plattsburg, and Capture of the British Fleet on Lake Champlain. The 11th Septr. 1814. To Accompany B. Tanner's Print of Macdonough's Victory.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Plan shows location of American and British forces in vicinity of Plattsburg during action on land, and position of American and British ships at naval engagement in Bay of Plattsburg. Companion to foregoing key. Duplicates of Nos. 299 (a) and 299 (b) supra.
    - Print No. 656. Aquatint: "To Captain H. Hope, the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion...", 1815 (Folder FF-5)
      "To Captain H. Hope, the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion, This Print representing the Morning after the Action with the American United States Frigate, President, Jany. 16th 1815 – which lasted two Hours and a half – is respectfully Dedicated by their obedient humble Servants, J. Burr & G. Ballisat." Painted by T. Buttersworth, the particulars & position of the Ships, by Lieut. Ormond, of the Endymion. Engraved by J. Jeakes. Published London, June 1st, 1815, by J. Burr & G. Ballisat, Gracechurch Steet. First state. Second of a pair of prints. Colored by hand. Duplicate of No. 326 supra.
    - Print No. 657. Aquatint: "The U.S. Squadron, under Command of Com. Decatur, At anchor off the City of Algiers, June 30th 1815.", 1816 (Folder FF-16)
      Engraved by G. Munger & S.S. Jocelin. New Haven: Published by N. Jocelin & G. Munger. Feb. 1816. Colored by hand.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (i) Miscellaneous Portraits (Folder -)
    - Print No. 667. Engraving: "Frankelin Ministre Plénipotentiare des Etats Unis de 'Amérique Septentrionale.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Written below in ink: "Né à Boston en 1706. Mort le 17 Avril 1790. àgé de 84." Dessiné par Bounieu d'après le Butte de M J Coudon. Gravé par Chevillet. Full bust oval portrait, without hat, set in rectangular frame. Face slightly toward right. In black and white.
    - Print No. 672. Engraving of John Dickinson, without title., undated (Folder FF-16)
      Drawn from life by Du Simitier in Philadelphia. Engraved by B. L. Prevost at Paris. No. II. In black and white. Undated. Companion to portrait of George Washington (No. 599).
    - Print No. 673. Mezzotint: "Major General John Sullivan A distinguish'd Officer in the Continental Army.", 1776 (Folder FF-16)
      "92" in lower right-hand corner. Artist and engraver not named. Publish'd as the Act directs 22 Augt. 1776 by Thos. Hart. Three-quarters length standing portrait in uniform; cocked hat on head. Face toward right. Long-handled pike in right hand. Left arm akimbo, with hilt of sword below. Tree at left. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 676. Stipple engraving: "Alexander Macomb, Major General U.S.A.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Autograph signature below title. Engraved by J.B. Longacre from a painting by T. Sully. Half-length portrait in uniform, without hat. Face front. Arms folded. Stauffer 2046. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 680. Lithograph: "The Presidents of the United States.", 1844 (Folder FF-16)
      Small portraits of the first eleven Presidents, Washington through President-elect Polk. Representation of the signing of the Declaration of Independence in center. Lith. by N. Currier. Copyrighted, 1844. Colored by hand.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplemental List. (j) Portraits of Naval Commanders (Folder -)
    - Print No. 681. Engraving: "Commodore Bainbridge.", undated (Folder FF-16)
      Painted by J. Jarvis. Engraved by Peter Maverick. Large full bust portrait in uniform, without hat. Face slightly toward right. Rectangle. In black and white.